<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Graph Database Blog - News and Tutorials from TerminusDB</title>
    <description>Graph Database Management news, tutorials and updates from TerminusDB
</description>
    <link>/bloghttps://terminusdb.com</link>
    <atom:link href="https://terminusdb.com/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 24 Nov 2020 11:24:48 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Nov 2020 11:24:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.7</generator>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      <item>
        <title>TerminusDB @ PyLadies Dublin</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello Terminators!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A first — for me at least — attending PyLadies, Dublin!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PyLadies helps more women become active participants and leaders in the Python open-source community. PyLadies Dublin also provides a friendly support network for women and a bridge to the larger Python world. Anyone with an interest in Python is encouraged to participate. You can see more &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/PyLadiesDublin/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; — we really enjoyed, so I’d encourage people to attend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TerminusDB Developer Advocate Extraordinaire, Cheuk, spoke at the PyLadies event earlier this week. There were about 40 PyLadies in the audience and a sprinkling of interloping PyMen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://miro.medium.com/max/9216/1*TyLh-oQIByoTjJ37rR3HzQ.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;PyLadiesDublin meetup&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event took place in the Dublin office of Qualtrics, which has a full replica of an Irish pub. Another good reason to attend!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheuk used TerminusDB to ask if we are supporting the correct politician. She used data from the Dublin City Council. It is a fascinating use case, and relevant in Ireland as we have just had an inconclusive election (and might have another in the not too distant future). There is a run through of the demo &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/01/15/are-you-supporting-the-right-politician/&quot;&gt;over here&lt;/a&gt; — give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full video of the excellent presentation is here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3XKJ9_bplUY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TerminusDB is open source now and forever so it is perfect for the Python community. We are rolling out ever more features for Pythonistas — check out our &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/01/20/design-a-query-language-client-for-pythonistas-and-data-scientists/&quot;&gt;python query client&lt;/a&gt;! And watch this space for exciting news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll keep you up to date with reports from TerminusDB talks and events. A veritable Terminator news service.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://terminusdb.com/blog/2020/02/21/terminusdb-pyladies-dublin/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://terminusdb.com/blog/2020/02/21/terminusdb-pyladies-dublin/</guid>
        
        <category>Python</category>
        
        <category>Database</category>
        
        <category>Data</category>
        
        <category>Data Science</category>
        
        <category>Politics</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
    
    
      <item>
        <title>Terminalia — Our Day</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The end of the year approaches. This Sunday 23 February we celebrate Terminalia — the festival that marks the end of the Old Roman Year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TerminusDB is named after the Roman God of boundaries, Terminus — all databases need good boundaries — and Terminalia is his festival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://miro.medium.com/max/1658/0*ArjA9ORibKUVEZFP.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;We want the finest wines available to humanity!&quot; /&gt;
We want the finest wines available to humanity!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terminus is an old Roman god — probably introduced by Romulus after the founding of the city. There is a famous story told of the last king of Rome, Tarquin (so disliked &amp;amp; proud that he was overthrown and the Republic declared) — he wanted to reshape Rome as an imperial capital and engaged in a large scale building programme. As part of his works, he set about reconstructing the Temple of Jupiter on the Capitol Hill. Tarquin thought that constructing a massive temple over the remains of a holy site consecrated by Romulus would cement his place as a great King of Rome. To facilitate the reconstruction, the older shrines to various gods had to be removed; however, when they attempted to move the shrine of Terminus, it would not budge. Terminus was the immovable rock of the Capitol. Even Jupiter, the king of the gods, had to kneel to Terminus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/terminusdb/terminusdb-whats-in-a-name-27b8be6b0794&quot;&gt;More on Terminus and TerminusDB’s name.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terminus’ slogan &lt;em&gt;‘Concedo Nulli’&lt;/em&gt; — concede to nobody — remains at the heart of the TerminusDB project. We continue to walk through walls to get the features out the door. We will not yield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://miro.medium.com/max/3792/0*QpWPQjM2KyznDjeD.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;statue of Terminus&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terminalia is the official holiday for TerminusDB. As it’s on a Sunday this year, we celebrate tonight. As Ovid dictates, we will allow the pagan spirits to flow. We will pour lamb’s blood on the statue of Terminus and offer him suckling pigs and wine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://miro.medium.com/max/2600/0*u1Y5gT-CQ3_Fx6bz.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;painting of Terminalia&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When night has passed, let the god be celebrated With customary honour, who separates the fields with his sign. Terminus, whether a stone or a stump buried in the earth, You have been a god since ancient times. You are crowned from either side by two landowners, Who bring two garlands and two cakes in offering. An altar’s made: here the farmer’s wife herself Brings coals from the warm hearth on a broken pot. The old man cuts wood and piles the logs with skill, And works at setting branches in the solid earth. Then he nurses the first flames with dry bark, While a boy stands by and holds the wide basket. When he’s thrown grain three times into the fire The little daughter offers the sliced honeycombs. Others carry wine: part of each is offered to the flames: The crowd, dressed in white, watch silently. Terminus, at the boundary, is sprinkled with lamb’s blood, And doesn’t grumble when a sucking pig is granted him. Neighbours gather sincerely, and hold a feast, And sing your praises, sacred Terminus: ‘You set bounds to peoples, cities, great kingdoms: Without you every field would be disputed. You curry no favour: you aren’t bribed with gold, Guarding the land entrusted to you in good faith. If you’d once marked the bounds of Thyrean lands, Three hundred men would not have died, Nor Othryades’ name be seen on the pile of weapons. O how he made his fatherland bleed! What happened when the new Capitol was built? The whole throng of gods yielded to Jupiter and made room: But as the ancients tell, Terminus remained in the shrine Where he was found, and shares the temple with great Jupiter. Even now there’s a small hole in the temple roof, So he can see nothing above him but stars. Since then, Terminus, you’ve not been free to wander: Stay there, in the place where you’ve been put, And yield not an inch to your neighbour’s prayers, Lest you seem to set men above Jupiter: And whether they beat you with rakes, or ploughshares, Call out: “This is your field, and that is his!”’ There’s a track that takes people to the Laurentine fields, The kingdom once sought by Aeneas, the Trojan leader: The sixth milestone from the City, there, bears witness To the sacrifice of a sheep’s entrails to you, Terminus. The lands of other races have fixed boundaries: The extent of the City of Rome and the world is one.” — Ovid, Fasti II&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.irishtimes.com/opinion/the-other-marching-season-terminalia-the-roman-festival-of-boundaries-1.3803276&quot;&gt;Terminalia and Terminus also sneak into Irish place names and traditional events&lt;/a&gt; (link to a great Irish Times article on the subject)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terminators around the world are encouraged to celebrate this momentous day. Wear white, sacrifice a lamb, let the spirit of pre-Republican Rome flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://miro.medium.com/max/2000/0*P0qHv01fUcd8XSMU.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;modern festival&quot; /&gt;
Get out there, Terminators&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://terminusdb.com/blog/2020/02/21/terminalia-our-day/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://terminusdb.com/blog/2020/02/21/terminalia-our-day/</guid>
        
        <category>Terminusdb</category>
        
        <category>Rome</category>
        
        <category>Database</category>
        
        <category>Party</category>
        
        <category>Do It Yourself</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      <item>
        <title>TerminusDB Discussions</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the really nice things about TerminusDB is our weekly get together where one team member gives a short presentation on something. It doesn’t have to be work, it doesn’t have to be TerminusDB, it can be anything really.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are a moderately distributed team and we have plenty of opportunity for detailed technical discussion (indexing strategy anyone?) so we thought that it’d be a good idea to start a less formal weekly exchange. One member of the team leads the discussion and the rest contribute with questions &amp;amp; comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the year and a bit since we started the tradition, we’ve had everything from the innards of JavaScript to Crypto Kitties to Theories of Developer Relations to Cloud Architecture to the Dialectics of Software Development (a personal favorite — I must post the slides).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://miro.medium.com/max/1602/1*AiOAyqAcjMq5qd8fBUdw2w.png&quot; alt=&quot;The right superstructure is important&quot; /&gt;
The right superstructure is important&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve also had nuclear power, the political economy of open source software, values vs virtues and Terry Davis (TempleOS is something else — I’d encourage all to check it out).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really whatever was of special interest to the person assigned that day. I looked back through the chat and realize that I have suggested ‘Practical Maoism for the Workplace’ twice and nobody has taken up my lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://miro.medium.com/max/1308/1*qa5C7ZG-4mvCH5KKJaUiLg.png&quot; alt=&quot;The system's features, such as its 640x480 resolution, 16-color display and single audio voice, were explicitly instructed to Terry Davis by God&quot; /&gt;
The system’s features, such as its 640x480 resolution, 16-color display and single audio voice, were explicitly instructed to Terry Davis by God&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tradition has grown to be an important part of every TerminusDB week. If we continue to grow the core group, I’m not sure how we’ll scale — 1 week in 30 might be a little infrequent. We can cross that bridge when we get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So anyway, we really value these discussions and thought the the broader Terminus Community might also enjoy. We’ve recorded the latest discussion, which took place yesterday, and uploaded it to our YouTube channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week we were led by our BDFL Gavin in a discussion of ‘Regular Expressions - Theory and Practice’. It covers a bunch of interesting aspects including Chomsky’s Hierarchy, Büchi automata, grammars and much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/mbtpAyn0n0o&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I apologize for the sound quality issues — we’ll work on a setup that captures the various contributors in high fidelity. At least you can hear the main presentation. Only one instance of adult language — less than normal I’d say — so be warned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be a regular series, so watch this space.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://terminusdb.com/blog/2020/01/28/terminusdb-discussions/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://terminusdb.com/blog/2020/01/28/terminusdb-discussions/</guid>
        
        <category>Database</category>
        
        <category>Development</category>
        
        <category>Programming</category>
        
        <category>Maoism</category>
        
        <category>Dialectics</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      <item>
        <title>TerminusDB 1.1 — The Big Babushka</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Another very big day for us — our first iteration on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/terminusdb/terminus-server&quot;&gt;TerminusDB goes out into the wild&lt;/a&gt;. We are calling it the &lt;strong&gt;Big Babushka&lt;/strong&gt; release as it has some huge changes to the way we manage data and the operations we support — it could almost be a 2.0, but given that we are a relatively young DB, we want to save those release numbers for future exciting developments (I did see another DB on release 0.50.0 — I won’t name names, but come on folks, give us a 1.0!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;terminus-store&quot;&gt;Terminus-store&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The major development is our new storage backend, terminus-store. With the introduction of the new store, TerminusDB takes a radical departure from traditional database architectures. Our approach has three parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We have a graph database with strong schema to retain simplicity and generality&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The graph is implemented using succinct immutable data structures which enable more sparing use of main memory resources.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We adopt a delta encoding approach to updates (‘like git, but for data’) which provides the whole suite of revision control features: branch, merge, squash, rollback, blame, and time-travel facilitating CI/CD approaches on data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This final point is crucial — with TerminusDB we can now use advanced CI/CD workflows in data operations. The large impact of git on the software development world can now be envisioned in the world of data. This is made possible by synergies between an immutable layered approach and the succinct data structure approach that we’ve used for encoding. The DevOps revolution becomes the DataOps revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as with DevOps, DataOps means a focus on collaboration, automation and integration. There is a requirement to bridge what is today a chasm between huge reams of unstructured data on the one hand, and analysts looking for access to simple, clean, structured data on the other. DataOps is that bridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TerminusDB is a practical tool for enabling branch, merge, rollback, and the various automated and manual testing regimes which they facilitate on a transactional database management system while providing sophisticated query support&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://miro.medium.com/max/1194/1*ADSnYco_5vlMbLT7eiT2Rw.png&quot; alt=&quot;showing how TerminusDB transections&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new TerminusDB store is implemented in Rust. It is low level, memory safe, has no run time and is C compatible. We think Rust will be the language of the 2020s and we are delighted to be Rustaceans!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/terminusdb/terminus-server/blob/dev/docs/whitepaper/terminusdb.pdf&quot;&gt;TerminusDB Technical Paper&lt;/a&gt; that goes into this in more detail for those interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://miro.medium.com/max/1678/1*S9ho_dXwojark-UnLrRSeQ.png&quot; alt=&quot;White Paper&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;woql&quot;&gt;WOQL&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Web Object Query Language — or WOQL — has developed considerably since our first release:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extended WOQL to greater functionality for string and arithmetic processing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Better date handling in WOQL&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improved type casting in WOQL&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improvements to query processing speed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growing maturity of WOQL provides a strong platform to import, clean and query complex data. WOQL remains the best graph query language available today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WOQL itself is specified as a JSON document format. All transmission of data uses the canonical JSON format, but this is generally annoying to write, hence WOQL.js is the preferred means by which human users can write queries manually. In developing WOQL we wanted to make querying graph data easy to learn, understand, and use, but also build on the power and functionality of other standard data access languages. As we can see from the TerminusDB tutorials, WOQL is a highly composable and flexible graph query language. Graphs are very generically applicable to a much wider range of data than table structured data. Ultimately, the flexibility of graphs with well specified schema, will show their value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;terminus--console&quot;&gt;Terminus — Console&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Console significantly builds on the simple JavaScript client application that released with 1.0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the query interface, you can now switch between WOQL.js and JSON. You can also add new queries to the original query — as inspired by the Jupyter Notebook functionality you know and love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://miro.medium.com/max/3474/1*uScpmhNCu0UwUR30Y_RGAA.png&quot; alt=&quot;TerminusDB console&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have run your query, we have a view interface to easily change the view on the output&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the console you now have the ability to toggle between table and graph view. On the query page, on the document page and on the schema page, you can see as a graph. This is super helpful when you are trying to see what’s in a complex schema, or trying to derive insight from a query.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Console gives user a quality interface for managing and querying TerminusDB. It ships with TerminusDB.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;python-client&quot;&gt;Python Client&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the release of the TerminusDB python client, python users can query data and interact with TerminusDB through the API and WOQL.py. We will continue to work to make TerminusDB more accessible for the python community (firstly, by improving our documentation!). TerminusDB is the database for data people, and there are no people that are more data than Pythonistas!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s Next&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are working hard on our collaboration and DataOps features. They should be available by the end of February 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll be pushing out documentation as fast as we can. There is lots of new stuff available, including a couple of tutorials, but it is never enough!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember we are open source (GPLv3) now and forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(And for anybody wondering, that’s CowDuck, our new mascot)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://terminusdb.com/blog/2020/01/16/terminusdb-1-1-the-big-babushka/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://terminusdb.com/blog/2020/01/16/terminusdb-1-1-the-big-babushka/</guid>
        
        <category>Developer Tools</category>
        
        <category>Data</category>
        
        <category>Database</category>
        
        <category>Python</category>
        
        <category>Rust</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
    
    
    
    
      <item>
        <title>Join the Data-Centric Revolution (we can help!)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you have had the &lt;strong&gt;pleasure&lt;/strong&gt; of attending a TerminusDB presentation, you might have heard something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Unified, well-designed &amp;amp; refined data will be the jet fuel of future business’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘The value of AI will not be realized unless we feed enough relationship-rich data to machines’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that the next generation of world-changing ideas will be powered by graphs. Graph databases, like TerminusDB, can do everything a relational database can do and then some. RDBMS are stable and feature rich with four decades of development under the belt; however, over time, DBMS will continue to drift towards graph. There will, of course, always be legacy systems hanging around doing useful stuff. We bump into plenty of pre-relational technology out here (especially MUMPS in the healthcare sector) and there are good reasons not to change things that work — ‘database migration’ sends shivers down the spines of even battle-hardened DBAs. In the years to come, new and innovative projects will be implemented on graph DBs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://miro.medium.com/max/2514/0*BqfeLvqCEA1CeDZN.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ranking from DB-Engines&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The time to shift to graph is very much now. There is an explosion of the number of databases, companies and projects using graph and we see legacy systems trying to squeeze graph models into places they don’t belong (we see you Datastax and MySQL). Native graph technology is now sufficiently mature to deliver value; hardware has come on-stream (as TerminusDB is an in-memory DB, big machines with lots of main memory are important for truly massive graphs); and organisations now understand the value in processing large amounts of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are database and data-ops people. In order to bring TerminusDB to life, we have poured years of high-intensity effort into building the database. Considerable innovation — both theoretical and practical — was required to get to this point. So we know how hard starting a project, an NGO, a company or anything else can be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is that we know about databases, but aren’t really so expert on other areas . Everywhere we look we see how data can be effectively applied to make the world better — we’re just not sure who will take the necessary steps. There is valuable, needle-moving data all around and it needs to be collected and queried effectively to make gains versus current standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is an area of human endeavor that is rich in data that is not being captured at present, there is a ripe opportunity to better understand. We are very aware of the possibilities in the area of research data — TerminusDB is the database behind ‘Seshat: the Global History Databank’, which seeks to systematically collect what is currently known about the social and political organization of human societies and how civilizations have evolved over time. When The Guardian recently ran a long piece about the project, some humanities scholars were vocally opposed to the very suggestion that data at scale could help us to understand the cycles of human history. We don’t agree. We think that there is a lot to learn — even about complex human systems — from organizing and querying large bodies of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://miro.medium.com/max/1636/1*5OyhpZkTAAGERGV8I5qcvw.png&quot; alt=&quot;TerminusDB Contributor in the Mix&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about the movements of shipping containers, the efficiency of wind farms, the items in the supermarket or the output of salespeople. Where there is high volume, high activity data, there are serious questions to ask. If you can properly collect, store and query that data, you can try to recommend a next best action. The value of this recommendation will compound over time. With enough data in a big enough graph, you’ll start to see network effects and understand your world at scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two industrial packaging plants next to each other. One has recorded data as a graph over many years and can query to see connections. The other fixes things when they break. The smart plant can start to predict with ever greater accuracy when things will stop working. Zero downtime is a massive and compounding advantage. One of these businesses will perform better over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linked knowledge allows you to train machines in best way possible. In future, instead of pulling data to generate reports, you can push data in packaged insights to inform the next step. This cybernetic approach to knowledge work can remove a lot of drudgery by minimizing choice and maximizing focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graph is the coming data model. The world will change, but some people haven’t seen it yet, so there is an opportunity. Unfortunately if you miss the data boat — it is difficult to catch up. The AI arms race is a zero sum game — those that use the data will win. We really, really want that to be the good guys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see a world full of opportunity, but can’t grasp it all. We call on startups, researchers, NGOs, government workers, factory operatives, hipsters, dreamers… anybody who thinks they can use data effectively to make the world a better place. TerminusDB is open source — released under the GPL v3 license — so there is no cost in using the database. We can offer you guidance, advice and encouragement. We believe that TerminusDB can offer value in a whole bunch of areas, and we want to help you realize that value. Join the data-centric revolution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://terminusdb.com/blog/2019/11/29/join-the-data-centric-revolution-we-can-help/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://terminusdb.com/blog/2019/11/29/join-the-data-centric-revolution-we-can-help/</guid>
        
        <category>Database</category>
        
        <category>Data</category>
        
        <category>Graph</category>
        
        <category>Terminusdb</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      <item>
        <title>TerminusDB — the database for data people.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;TerminusDB is open source now and forever. We are releasing with the GPL V3 licence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The development of Terminus has been a nine-year labour of love, devotion, frustration and pain. You can imagine how delighted we are to release TerminusDB to the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have designed TerminusDB for the web age. We wanted to make something that greatly reduced the time and effort required to build any application that shares, manipulates or edits data. TerminusDB is a unified model database; it has the most desirable features of graph, semantic, document and time-series database alternatives. With WOQL, the model aware query language, Terminus allows you to query your data flexibly and quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope that TerminusDB will make the life of anybody who cares about data — and particularly the long term value of well curated data — much easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core team will be working on improving Terminus over the coming months, years and decades. We hope you’ll join us on this journey as a user, contributor or enthusiast. The database of the future needs you — join the data-centric revolution!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.terminusdb.com/&quot;&gt;terminusdb.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(We live for GitHub stars, so please go and star Terminus: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/terminusdb/terminus-server&quot;&gt;https://github.com/terminusdb/terminus-server&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/terminusdb_logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;TerminusDB logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://terminusdb.com/blog/2019/10/01/today-we-release-terminusdb-the-database-for-data-people/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://terminusdb.com/blog/2019/10/01/today-we-release-terminusdb-the-database-for-data-people/</guid>
        
        <category>Model</category>
        
        <category>Data</category>
        
        <category>Database</category>
        
        <category>Graph Database</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
      <item>
        <title>TerminusDB — what’s in a name?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;TerminusDB is an open source model driven graph database for knowledge graph representation designed specifically for the web-age. Our launch date is 1 October later this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/images/terminusdb_logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;TerminusDB logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core development team is busy putting the pieces into place and we are all really excited about bringing TerminusDB to the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll be pushing out plenty of content and documentation about the capabilities of the database over the coming weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have long dreamed of a future where databases learn by automatically extracting information both from existing networked data-sources and from their users to continuously improve the reliability and accuracy of the information they contain. We wanted to build a database that would be capable of automatically generating sophisticated curation and analysis tools to allow users to access and manage the data they contain and to feed the results of these analyses into real-time automated workflows and learning algorithms. A big ask, but TerminusDB will be a strong step towards making it a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://miro.medium.com/max/1334/1*HleRZdBTjZqwcOBkeY8x2g.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;BDFL Gavin Mendel-Gleason&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Benevolent Dictator for Life is the one and only Gavin Mendel-Gleason. He’s a database maniac who dreams of logic, mathematics and formal methods. Gavin and the rest of the team have poured years of high-intensity work into building TerminusDB. Considerable innovation — both theoretical and practical — was required to build the database. Not only did we end up having to write the software ourselves, along the way we had to develop and formalise a new theoretical model of computer programming for data intensive systems; develop, formalise and prove a new modular logic for data objects; and devise, develop and deploy a new general purpose logical approach to describing and querying graph shapes and constraining their transitions. It has been a labour of love by all the contributing team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://miro.medium.com/max/672/1*f8egU0CASEEqGPmvma8Gyg.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Immovable &amp;amp; Persistent&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terminus was the Roman god of boundaries. He is an old Roman god — probably introduced by Romulus after the founding of the city. There is a famous story told of the last king of Rome (so disliked &amp;amp; proud that he was overthrown and the Republic declared) — he wanted to reshape Rome as an imperial capital and engaged in a large scale building programme. As part of his works, he set about reconstructing the Temple of Jupiter on the Capitol Hill. Tarquin thought that constructing a massive temple over the remains a holy site consecrated by Romulus would cement his place as a great King of Rome. To facilitate the reconstruction, the older shrines to various gods had to be removed; however, when they attempted to move the shrine of Terminus, it would not budge. Terminus was the immovable rock of the Capitol. Even Jupiter, the king of the gods, had to kneel to Terminus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://miro.medium.com/max/1658/1*lF_rZhXDtYOeBrEV1_3qLw.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;The Feast Before the Altar of Terminus. (c. 1642) By Giovanni Benedetto Castiglione (1609–1664)&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ovid, the great Roman poet, writing 500 years later, interpreted these events:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘What happened when the new Capitol was built?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Where he was found, and shares the temple with great Jupiter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Even now there’s a small hole in the temple roof,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So he can see nothing above him but stars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Since then, Terminus, you’ve not been free to wander:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Stay there, in the place where you’ve been put,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And yield not an inch to your neighbour’s prayers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Lest you seem to set men above Jupiter.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terminus, as the God of boundaries, is particularly appropriate for our database management system. All good databases need boundaries — you need to know what’s in there and what isn’t. One of our major innovations in building TerminusDB is implementing a closed world version of OWL, the web ontology language. In the semantic web academic tradition, OWL has an open world assumption which means that the truth value of a statement may be true irrespective of whether or not it is known to be true. For TerminusDB any statement that is true must also be known to be true. This makes the database practical and usable for a broad range of industrial applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://miro.medium.com/max/844/1*J__EDmwjRNNVu4EkAbUEXA.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Design for a Stained Glass Window with Terminus. (31 December 1524) By Hans Holbein the Younger.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Roman God Terminus’ slogan ‘Concedo Nulli’ — concede to nobody — is also particularly appealing to the core TerminusDB team. As anybody who has delivered a production ready database will know, you have to walk through walls to get it done and yield to nobody. We bear the scars of those battles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://miro.medium.com/max/600/1*FTRE73m34GjDViAY1W25AA.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Terminus is the capital planet of the 1st Foundation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asimov fans will also recognise Terminus as the home planet of the Foundation. Hari Seldon, inventor of Psychohistory, predicted a 30,000 year interregnum of barbaric dark ages until the rise of a New Empire. Seldon created a plan to shorten this interregnum from 30,000 years to 1,000 years. The Foundation was set up as an organisation intent on preserving all of human knowledge during the 1,000 years of chaos. Seldon’s true intention for the Foundation was to preserve the sciences and provide a political starting point for the Second Empire. The Foundation grows from Terminus to become a federation of planets under the direct control of Terminus or under its sphere of influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TerminusDB powers Seshat, the Global History Databank, which is like the Foundation in that Seshat is dedicated to bringing together the most current and comprehensive body of knowledge about human history in one place. The massive collection of historical information allows researchers to rigorously test different hypotheses about the rise and fall of large-scale societies and human history. The core TerminusDB team are active in the Cliodynamics community. Cliodynamics treats history as science — practitioners develop theories that explain such dynamic historical processes, translate these theories into mathematical models and then test predictions against data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://miro.medium.com/max/1814/1*kCm-Owh43PHf5h7UF-Oy8w.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;‘Ages of Discord’ by Peter Turchin&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The father of Cliodynamics, Peter Turchin, recently authored a book ‘Ages of Discord’, which uses cliodynamic approaches and the data in the Global History Databank to give an insight into the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parallels to Asimov’s psychohistory are very strong. Cliodynamics is the real world version of psychohistory and Seshat is the real world version of the Foundation. And TerminusDB is the analogue of Terminus in the Foundation universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want people around the world to use our database, but we also want you to contribute to the project. We believe in the ideals of the free software movement. We’ll therefore release TerminusDB under GPL V3. That will allow everybody to inspect and use the full code base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe in a data-centric approach to development. Hoarding data in proprietary and complex applications is a mistake. Validation logic should be embedded in the data layer where it belongs and not housed in expensive to maintain application code. Long term cost of data ownership has been a huge consideration as we worked on this project.
TerminusDB contributors will be posting on this blog over the coming weeks and months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://miro.medium.com/max/400/1*_xTYaO0GlB_pyVCzb1AMJg.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;we can do it&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Join the data-centric revolution!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://terminusdb.com/blog/2019/08/21/terminusdb-whats-in-a-name/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://terminusdb.com/blog/2019/08/21/terminusdb-whats-in-a-name/</guid>
        
        <category>Machine Learning</category>
        
        <category>Terminus</category>
        
        <category>Database</category>
        
        <category>Data</category>
        
        <category>Development</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>
